Grace Harriet Spofford papers SSC.MS.00150
Sophia Smith Collection
Grace Harriet Spofford papers
1795-1974
1935-1954
Sophia Smith Collection
Spofford, Grace Harriet, 1888-1974
SSC.MS.00150
23 boxes (12.25 linear feet)
Teacher; Musician; Music administrator. Papers include correspondence, diaries, memorabilia, speeches, writings, sheet music, photographs, and subject files on women in music. There are also a large number of files on organizations and conferences (primarily music-related), including the Music School of the Henry Street Settlement, the International Music Council of UNESCO, and the International Council of Women and National Council of Women.
Biographical / Historical
Grace Spofford was born in 1887 in Haverhill, MA. She studied piano from age seven and entered Mt. Holyoke College in 1905, transferring after one year to Smith College. After receiving an A.B. from Smith in 1909, Spofford taught piano at Heidelberg College in Tiffin, OH, and gave recitals in small towns in the midwest. In 1912, she went to Peabody Conservatory in Baltimore, MD, where she studied piano and organ, taught piano, wrote music criticism for the Baltimore Evening Sun, and published A Guide for Beginners in Piano Playing (1916) with her lifelong friend Elizabeth Coulson. An injury combined with a love of administrative work led to jobs as Executive Secretary at Peabody (1917-24) and first Dean of the newly established Curtis Institute of Music (1924-31) in Philadelphia. After moving to NY in 1931, she worked as Associate Director of the NY College of Music, Executive Secretary of Layman's Music Courses, and manager of the Curtis String Quartet. In 1935 Spofford became Director of the Music School of the Henry Street Settlement where she worked to de-professionalize music and encourage widespread participation in music "shared as a common experience of life." After her retirement in 1954, Spofford represented the U.S. at many national and international music and music education conferences, was a delegate to the International Music Council of UNESCO, and served on the International and National Councils of Women. She died in 1974.
Scope and Contents
TThe Grace Spofford Papers consist of biographical material, correspondence, diaries, business papers (mostly financial), memorabilia, speeches, writings, sheet music, photographs, organization files, and subject files. The bulk of the material is the files on organizations (primarily music-related) for which and with which Spofford worked. There are also a large number of subject files on women in music including biographical files on individual women musicians. Though there is one item dated 1795, the bulk of the materials are dated from 1935 to 1954.
Related Material
Additional material located in Smith College Archives.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Initial accessions were received on the following dates: 1960-1975. Additional items were added in 2018.
Female friendship--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Social settlements--New York (State)--New York--History--Sources; Women musicians--United States--Biography--Sources; Women composers--United States--Biography--Sources; Women--Societies and clubs--United States--History--Sources; correspondence; photographs; diaries; Business records; Speeches; Writings; Ephemera; Sheet music; Spofford, Grace Harriet, 1888-1974; Henry Street Settlement (New York, N.Y.); International Council of Women--History--Sources; National Council of Women of the United States--History--Sources; Barko, Dorothy; Spofford, Grace; Spofford, Grace Harriet
- Grace Harriet Spofford papers, 1795-1974; 1935-1954
  - Biography
    - Sarah and Harry H. Spofford: clippings and obituaries, 1918-21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Elizabeth Coulson: articles, obituaries, photographs, 1865-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Passports and birth certificate, 1887-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Genealogy (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Biographical material, 1906-74 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clippings, 1928-69 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Smith College: commencement book, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Baby's journal, 1887 (Grace Spofford's) (Box 1)
    - Elizabeth Coulson scrapbook, 1895-1905 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Photograph album: Smith College (Box 1)
    - Grace Spofford (Box 1)
      - Alone, 1909; undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - With groups, 1918-66 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Henry Street Settlement, 1936-37; undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Director's Conference, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Brussels, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Miscellaneous, 1919-66 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified, 1953; undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Framed photographs: Harry and Sarah Spofford (3); Elizabeth Coulson (1) (Box 2)
    - Photo album: from Parent's Association of the Music School of Henry Street Settlement, 1954 (Box 2)
    - 2 photo albums, undated (Box 2)
  - Diaries
    - 1898-1939 (Box 3)
    - 1941-72 (Box 3a)
  - Business papers
    - Correspondence, 1933-49; 1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Insurance and miscellaneous documents, 1932-67 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
    - Cancelled checks, 1947-53 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
    - Federal income tax returns, 1942-52; 1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence
    - Letters of recommendation and introduction, 1912-60 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Outgoing (Box 5)
      - 1924-71 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
      - Lillian Wald, 1936-40 (Box 5)
    - Incoming
      - A-B, 1931-68; undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Dorothy S. Ainsworth, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Marian Anderson, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Derek Bok, 1970-71 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Mary L.C. Bok, 1926-30 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Styles Bridges, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - C, 1931-72 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Grace Coolidge, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Aaron Copeland, 1954-67 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Elizabeth Coulson, 1929-40; undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - D, 1931-69 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Judith Dvorkin, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - E-F, 1931-72 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Geraldine Farrar, 1937-38 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - Kirsten Flagstad, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - G, 1924-70 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - George Gershwin, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - Peggy Glanville-Hicks, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
      - Morton Gould, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 23)
      - H-I, 1927-71 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - J-K, 1931-71 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Jacob Javits, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Olga Koussevitzky (Mrs. Serge), 1955-73 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - L, 1953-60 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Fiorello LaGuardia, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Miscellaneous (unidentified), 1940-73 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - M, 1932-73 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Newbold Morris, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Robert Moses, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - George Murphy, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - N-O, 1931-61 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Richard Neuberger, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Lawrence O'Brien, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - P-O, 1945-69 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - Claiborne Pell, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - R, 1927-71 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - Fritz Reiner, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - S, 1931-73 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Harold Schonberg, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - Leopold Stokowski, 1927-54 (Box 6, Folder 21)
      - Eleanor Steber, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 22)
      - Gladys Swarthout, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - T, 1930-60 (Box 6, Folder 24)
      - V-Z, 1943-73 (Box 6, Folder 25)
      - Lillian D. Wald, 1935-39 (Box 6, Folder 26)
      - Walter Bruno, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 27)
      - Efrem and Mary Curtis Zimbalist, 1941-56 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Memorabilia
    - Trips (Box 6)
      - Europe, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Middle East, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Memories of the Gripsolm Cruise to the Lands of the Vikings and Russia, 1943 (Box 7)
    - Awards and Citations, 1951-69 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Autograph book, 1927-31 (Box 7)
  - Writings
    - Articles and clippings, 1934-69 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - "Thoughts of a Musicologist,", 1969 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Speeches
    - 1924-66, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - "On international understanding,", 1954 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Notes
    - Radio talks, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - New York Leisure Time Commission, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 1917-73, undated (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
  - Pamphlets and blank postcards, 1921-72 (Box 9)
  - Printed music scores, 1916-41; undated (Box 10)
  - Wisdom in Miniature or the Young Gentleman and Lady's Pleasing Instructor, 1795 (Box 10)
  - Organizations
    - American International Music Fund, Inc., 1958 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Asian Music Circle, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Beekman Hill Neighbors, 1930-35 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Cleveland Music School Settlement, 1956-72 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Committee of Correspondence, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Federal Music Project, 1936-46 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Folk Festival Council of New York, 1933-34 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Foreign Service Institute, 1955-57 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Fortnightly Music Club of Cleveland, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Curtis Institute of Music
      - Articles and clippings, 1928-39 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Forms, 1924-30 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - Concert programs, invitations and miscellaneous, 1924-31 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - Catalogs, 1924-49 (Box 12)
      - Recital and concert programs, 1925-31 (Box 13)
      - Overtones, 1929-37 (monthly publication) (Box 14)
    - Henry Street Settlement (Box 14)
      - Music School (Box 14)
        - Memorabilia and printed material, 1939-54 (Box 15, Folder 1)
        - Clippings, 1935-53 (Box 15, Folder 2)
        - Calendars, 1945-53 (Box 15, Folder 3)
        - Commencement, 1943-53 (Box 15, Folder 4)
        - Publicity, 1938-50 (Box 15, Folder 5)
        - Twenty-fifth anniversary, 1925 (Box 15, Folder 6)
        - Annual reports, 1935-52 (Box 15, Folder 7)
        - "Bulletin,", 1954 (Box 15, Folder 8)
        - Programs, 1931-62 (Box 15, Folder 9)
        - Retirement, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 10)
      - School of Drama, Playhouse, 1937-50 (Box 15, Folder 11)
      - Unfinished Business, a firsthand account of the former director of the Henry Street Settlement by Helen Hall, New York, 1971 [on shelf] (Box 15)
    - International Conference on The Role of Music in the Education of Youth and Adults, 1953 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - International Congress for Professional Education of Musicians, 1953 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - International Council of Women
      - Music competitions for women musicians, 1958-66 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Standing Committee on the Arts and Letters (Box 16)
        - Reports, 1955-69 (Box 16, Folder 4)
        - Questionnaires, 1958-64 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - International Music Conference, 1953-68 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - International Music Council, 1951-68 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - International Society for Music Education, 1957-58 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Julliard School, 1942-69 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Katherine Gibbs School, 1949-59 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Koussevitzky Music Foundation, undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Layman's Music Course, Inc., 1934-35 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Mu Phi Epsilon, 1958-74 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Municipal Art Committee, City of New York, 1932-39 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Municipal Broadcasting Station Subcommittee, 1935-36 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Music Education Conference, 1931 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Music Educators National Conference, 1953 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Music for Youth, Japan, 1958; undated (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Musicians Club of New York, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Musicians Emergency Aid of New York, 1932 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - National Advisory Council on Radio in Education, 1930-35 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - National Arts Club, 1962-72 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - National Arts Guild, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - National Council of Women
      - Printed material, 1953-64 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Music Committee (Box 18)
        - Concerts and lectures, 1957-64 (Box 18, Folder 2)
        - Radio broadcasts, 1951-65 (Box 18, Folder 3)
        - Reports and minutes, 1953-64 (Box 18, Folder 4)
        - Miscellaneous, 1956-62 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - National Federation of Music Clubs, 1958-69 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - National Federation of Settlements
      - General, 1940; undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - Music Division, 1926-48 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - National Guild of Community Music Schools, 1946-72 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - National Music Council, 1954-72 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - National Recreation Association, 1941; undated (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - National Youth Administration, 1939-41 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Neighborhood Music Schools, Inc., 1949 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - New York Association of Music School Settlements, 1931-43 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - New York City Music Council, 1945 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - New York College of Music, 1934-52 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - New York Federation of Music Clubs, 1968-72 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - New York State Board of Education, 1950; undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Peabody Institute
      - Miscellaneous, 1912-71 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Publications, 1938-71 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - People to People, Music Committee, 1957-58 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Philharmonic Symphony Sociey of New York, 1933-57 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Philippine Women's University, 1963-65 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Pipers Guild of America, 1941 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Radio Institute of the Audible Arts, 1934-35 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Rural Music Schools Association, 1949-53 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Smith College
      - Club of New York, Class of, 1909; 1954-70 (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - Board of Counselors, Music Committee, 1950-58 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Society of Women Musicians, 1954 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Turtle Bay Music School, 1945 (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Unitarian Church of All Souls, N.Y., 1969-73 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - United Nations, 1951; undated (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - UNESCO, 1956-57 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - United Nations Conference (International House), 1956-57 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - United Neighborhood Houses, 1942-43; undated (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Women United for the United Nations, 1967 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Women's Alliance, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Works Progress Administration, 1934-43 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - World Association for Adult Education, 1931 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Young Audiences, undated (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - YWCA, 1934; undated (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Subjects
    - Kennedy Center, 1967 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Music (Box 22)
      - Asia, 1952-58; undated (Box 22, Folder 2)
      - Clippings, 1915-58 (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - Veterans/War effort, 1942-45 (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - Youth, 1944-51; undated (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Music Education, Philippines, 1955-63 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Music, USA, 1964 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Radio, 1930-51 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Recreation, 1942-58 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Women, 1928-61 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Young People's Concert, 1964 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Women in music, 1914-57 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Composers, 1959-69 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - Esther Ballou, undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - Joyce Barthelson, 1963-68 (Box 23, Folder 4)
      - Gena Branscome, 1962 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - Mabel Wheeler Daniels, 1961; undated (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - Emma Lou Diemer, 1964-68 (Box 23, Folder 7)
      - Judith Dvorkin, undated (Box 23, Folder 8)
      - Vivian Fine, 1963; undated (Box 23, Folder 9)
      - Elizabeth Gest, undated (Box 23, Folder 10)
      - Peggy Glanville-Hicks, 1954-64; undated (Box 23, Folder 11)
      - Elizabeth Gould, undated (Box 23, Folder 12)
      - Mary Howe, 1955-64 (Box 23, Folder 13)
      - Wanda Landowska, 1960 (Box 23, Folder 14)
      - Frances McCollin, undated (Box 23, Folder 15)
      - Elizabeth Lutyens and Elizabeth Maconchy, 1963 (Box 23, Folder 16)
      - Florence Jepperson Madeson, undated (Box 23, Folder 17)
      - Ursula Mamlok, 1965 (Box 23, Folder 18)
      - Dorothy Mayner, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 19)
      - Bernice Morrison Morris, undated (Box 23, Folder 20)
      - Carolyn Allen Perera, 1963 (Box 23, Folder 21)
      - Julia Perry, undated (Box 23, Folder 22)
      - Jean Reti-Forbes, 1967; undated (Box 23, Folder 23)
      - Philippa Schulyer, 1960 (Box 23, Folder 24)
      - Netty Simons, undated (Box 23, Folder 25)
      - Julia Smith, 1968 (Box 23, Folder 26)
      - Louise Talma, 1963 (Box 23, Folder 27)
      - Ninon Vallin, 1972 (Box 23, Folder 28)
      - Mme. Vengerova, undated (Box 23, Folder 29)
      - Elinor Remick Warren, undated (Box 23, Folder 30)
      - Mary Weaver, undated (Box 23, Folder 31)
      - Vally Weigl, 1949-58 (Box 23, Folder 32)
- OVERSIZED MATERIALS
  - Scrapbooks, 1909-31; 1922-24 (Box 24)
  - Santayana, George, tr.: "The Music Of The Spheres" (Box 24)
  - Photograph, diplomas, and certificates, undated; 1904-1952 (Map-case Flat file drawer 9)